[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine
online at computer.org software
sc radio listeners we want to hear from
you
please visit se radio.net slash survey
to share a little information about your
professional interests and listening
habits it takes less than two minutes to
help us continue to make se radio even
better
your responses to the survey are
completely confidential that's
s-e-radio.net survey
thanks for your support of the show we
look forward to hearing from you soon
welcome to software engineering radio
i'm your host jeff doolittle i'm very
excited to invite epec uskaya as our
guest on the show today to discuss her
book managing technical debt reducing
friction in software development epec is
the author of the book along with their
co-authors philippe cretchen and robert
nord epec is a technical director at the
carnegie mellon software engineering
institute she develops techniques for
improving software development
efficiency and system evolution she
regularly works with government and
industry organizations to improve their
software architecture practices
she received a phd in computational
design from carnegie mellon university
and is editor-in-chief of ieee software
magazine the publisher of software
engineering radio epec welcome to the
show
well thanks for having me jeff your book
is titled managing technical debt
reducing friction in software
development why should listeners care
about technical wealth
oh well why shouldn't they
so
i think we revisit the problem of
software maintenance and evolution and
software quality software over and over
again every once in a couple years
there's a major failure that happens
that attracts all of our attention then
we're like okay we need to change the
way we develop software and then we
forget about it
we
by we i mean the software engineering
community and software organizations
really care about new functionality they
develop they do care about their defects
they do care about their security issues
vulnerabilities somehow they don't care
as much about the fundamental design
problems that actually bite them in the
long run and i think technical that is
as a concept really puts that
up at the front of the developers
software architects as well as decision
makers project managers that's reason
one for them to care about it
the other reason is if they don't care
about technical debt
in the long run
they will have to deal with it one way
or another and that might be too late so
that also is another reason to care
about technical debt so ignore it at
your own peril exactly ignore it at your
own peril and i think i mean it's not a
new concept it was put out in 1992
and we've kind of gone around and we
keep referencing it and whatnot however
what is actually has been new especially
in the past couple of years is
developers recognize it now they're
talking about
okay this is going to create more rework
if we don't address some of these
fundamental design
issues that have been introduced over
time into the software and i think
that's important for us to recognize as
well
you made an interesting connection now
twice between technical debt and design
and i think that's an important
connection to make so maybe you can
expand on that a little bit and as you
do help us understand what you mean when
you say technical debt because i
sometimes wonder if we all mean the same
thing when we use that term so when we
talk about technical debt what we're
referring to are the shortcuts that
development teams take sometimes for
good reason
maybe they haven't implemented the
software as decoupled as they wanted
maybe they did not incorporate an
external
system that they wanted to include that
with the knowledge that as they keep
developing the software they will have
to change it to rework it so that's the
notion of technical debt how it relates
to architecture is all of these kinds of
shortcuts are actually architectural
nature they are about the structure and
behavior of the system when you take a
shortcut you do not want to decouple the
different functionality in different
modules or you don't want to upgrade the
software that you had to upgrade those
are the kinds of shortcuts that actually
have impact in terms of the design and
architectural decisions and why
technical that is powerful we already
have concepts that we refer to other
aspects of the software development life
cycle we know how to talk about use
cases and stories and new functionality
and ethics we know how to talk about
defects and bugs as we develop the
software we don't have to talk about the
vulnerabilities while we do talk about
architecture and design we don't have
these bite-sized concepts that help us
to manage them as we go through sprint
boundaries as we go through prioritizing
a design rework versus adding new
functionality so that's i think why it's
important for addressing both from a
definition perspective as well as
relating it to design and architecture
okay
so the book starts with the word
managing why manage technical debt
wouldn't it be better to just eliminate
it all together
first of all i know i will refer to
these but one of the principles we have
as those who read the book will realize
is that any system and every system has
technical debt and it's you're not going
to be able to eliminate technical debt
that's for sure so managing is that's
the right way to approach it because if
you don't manage it it's going to
accumulate and also managing provides
the whole benefit
the reason technical that is important
and why it's powerful to relate to the
financial concept is there's a benefit
to it when you take a shortcut or when
you decide not to
implement it in the way the best way
that might sustain you for the long term
you're actually creating a benefit
delivering it faster or being able to
address some value proposition in the
organization so that benefit requires to
be managed similar to how we manage our
market right we don't just forget it and
paid in lump sum in 30 years we pay it
in regular intervals and whatnot so it's
really that management aspect of the
debt
that might create value it's management
aspect of the technical that in the
software will that will create value as
well so that's why it's management
yeah an interesting you mentioned
you know financial as an analogy and it
has debt in it so that is interesting
although you know 100 years ago they
didn't have mortgages like we do now if
you wanted to buy a house it was 50 down
and a balloon payment in five years so
that's a way to manage your technical
debt but that's not what you're
describing you're talking about more
like paying it down as you go right hand
it down as you go
deciding not to pay down as you go
because it might be that might be in
parts of the system that doesn't change
often that might be in parts of the
system that you're going to retire and
also take it on
knowing that it's you're actually
creating some value i also very strongly
believe some aspects of technical debt
can actually help you like for example
you're going to learn something and then
you're going to decide on the best
design choice that actually has a lot of
value and until you rework that part of
the system that's actually value added
because you're collecting information
so when would you say that it becomes
technical debt because what you just
described there i you know a process
that i use we start with a detailed
design phase and then the idea is you
have to throw that away you don't get to
keep that in the concept there is you
have a set of requirements we know
requirements change but we're going to
take a whack at it and the result of
that actually should be refined
interfaces you know speaking of
architecture and refined contracts
between you know how this new thing
we're building is going to interact or
what it's going to offer the other
things that you're going to build so
i think i might have just answered the
question myself so maybe
yeah so when would that actually become
technical debt if maybe you're in a
design phase and you're not actually
going to put it into production for
example so i think you
bring up a very important and subtle
point because for example if you're
going through a prototyping or design
exploration phase in your software
development you might know that i'm not
going to use this i'm going to throw it
away but there's always that one percent
chance that it might actually stay on
the system so
one approach could be well this is a
throwaway prototype that we're doing but
if it stays on these are the ways it
might become technical that when it
becomes technical that is when you start
observing the negative consequences what
might be negative consequences maybe
you're trying it out but you didn't
design for some of the available
scalability or other resource
requirements or
you're designing it with underlying
subsystem that you're relying on but you
don't have
rights to it it needs to be purchased
then if it's put into production there
are those boundaries so there are all
aspects of consequences and when those
consequences will actually start to be
observed then it really becomes
technical that that has higher interest
as opposed to zero interest when you
were prototyping through it so i think
it really is important and that's
actually what we emphasize with my
co-authors robert nord and philippe
curtin in the book it's the
understanding the consequences and
managing it to the consequences if
you're able to manage the consequences
it's zero percent interest rate then
it's okay to maybe keep the technical
debt on for a while yeah and as we go
we'll dig i think a little bit more into
how you compare technical debt to you
know the finance world and then i think
it's a really helpful analogy but before
we dive into the principles which you
referred to before the nine principles
of technical debt management early in
the introduction to the book you
reference what edsger dykstra in 1972
called the software crisis
so i would imagine that from you and
your co-author's perspective you would
say the industry maybe still is in
crisis and if so how is that relevant to
this subject in particular about
technical
the software industry is in crisis
there's one report after another that
comes i don't always pay too much
attention to those because there's this
added fear happens and there's all sorts
of business context but i think the
software industry is in crisis and has
been in crisis the reason being first of
all we're relying on it a lot
increasingly the complexity of the
software is increased and the complexity
is also from the interactions right a
lot of software interact with other
software there's this ecosystem of
software we're creating we have a crisis
because we can't create developers in
the rate that we need them in terms of
the skill sets that are required
it's a there's a crisis that technology
changes incredibly quickly and we don't
always have to catch up so all of these
things and what we call in the book is
like a debt by a thousand cuts there's a
cut that happens every day in the
software and some organizations manage
it better than others and i think while
we appreciate
technical debt we call it technical debt
today but we also appreciate software
maintenance evolution and
maintainability and sustainability
perspectives
that crisis will not go away we don't
have tools we don't have vocabulary to
talk about what might be accumulating
through time in the software and i think
that's important to relate technical
debt to that complexity and the software
crisis
we think things will actually
fall in place in the right way but it
doesn't we still have some of the crisis
and i'm not going to name any
organizations or any part but
i think every week we have a news that
is with significant software that
actually creates
life-threatening risks not only
financial ones so that's not going to go
away and i think the power of technical
debt and managing technical that it
provides that vocabulary as well as the
tool sets for organizations to
be maybe honest with themselves
right and maybe they can
reduce the amount of crisis in their
context and if enough people start doing
that we you know may not fix the whole
industry but maybe the beginnings of
that can start to come to fruition
well let's start diving into these nine
principles of technical debt management
that you refer to in the book so the
first one states that technical debt
reifies an abstract concept so
first off i don't know if a lot of our
listeners use the word refi often in
their day-to-day conversation so
speaking of abstract concepts but
maybe you can start by defining reify
for us and then explain how that
describes the relationship between
technical debt and abstract concepts
so
english as a second language speaker i
will admit that when that word was
actually part of our principles i
personally had to go back and check okay
is that really the best word we use but
it is the best way to use because what
it means is technical that is an
abstract concept right we're talk
especially in software that's why we
keep talking about what is the
definition how do i put my head around
it is everything that goes bad in my
software technical then so it takes that
abstract concept and in this book what
we are aiming to do is make it concrete
and the way we make it concrete is we
say
first of all separate your causes from
your technical debt your yes
your manager who may not have made the
right decision at the right time may
have created a cause for technical debt
but that's the cause yes the
documentation not existing might be a
cause of technical debt yes the
requirements not illustrated might be a
cause of technical debt but those are
the causes
the debt itself that you want to manage
is actually something that you can
define and put your hand around in the
software system
you should be able to say here is the
rework that needs to happen in the
software here are the consequences that
happen if we don't do that rework and
those consequences are in terms of
harder things to add to the software or
additional defects that you might be
introducing and whatnot so that
concreteness is what we're really going
after with that principle so if you are
not able to get it at that level of
concreteness then maybe there are other
concepts in the software engineering
life cycle and the practices we have
that might be better suited for the
problem you're dealing with well and
it's interesting too you mentioned
avoiding focus so much on the cause
because
that often doesn't help you move forward
unless you're doing root cause analysis
to avoid the same problem in the future
which makes sense but if it's turning
into the blame game it's not really
helping you it's better to just say
here's what it is and so
to reify sounds like it means to make
concrete
correct so technical debt makes these
abstract concepts about what's wrong and
how did we get here and why is this hit
difficult and why is it getting harder
and it makes it concrete gives us
concrete concepts that we can discuss we
can analyze we can evaluate and make
decisions based on those actions is that
a good summary of that i could not agree
more and also furthermore and that's
also what we emphasize in the book is
you can concretely point it to the
actual place in the code or some of
those software development artifacts
that you need to change for technical
debt to disagree okay so it helps us
connect these abstract nebulous things
something's wrong
and we have various ways of thinking
about something being wrong you
mentioned before you know you have
technical debt when you start seeing the
cost right
something's wrong but now to be able to
say okay i have a framework i have a set
of concepts that i can use to sort of
make these things concrete and
distinguish things like you know the
root cause isn't related to the actual
debt itself and i can start
distinguishing those concepts it really
sounds like in some ways this first
principle is telling us the book is
offering us a way to think about
technical debt by defining it and giving
us ways to
sort of categorize it analyze it and
begin making strategies for addressing
it correct and especially for addressing
it the way you might address causes
might be completely different will be
completely different not might more than
how you actually pay down the technical
that that already exists like for
example if developer turnover is
creating all these confusion and each
new developer that comes on introduces a
new piece of complexity or mistake into
the code
that's a different problem and the
strategies to fix that are completely
different than going into the code base
and fixing the problems that they have
introduced so that strategies will be
different so i think decoupling them is
important so don't refer to developer
turnover as your technical that refer to
the mistakes that they have made and
document them and some of them may not
be technical that some of them will be
just defects or whatnot so i think it's
important from that aspect as well okay
and we'll dig a little bit more into
that later because you just made a
distinction between technical dead and
defects and it will be good to dive a
little bit more into that in a bit but i
think part of the distinction there
you're making is between the symptoms
and the diagnosis you know the symptoms
might be we have technical debt and we
have defects we have these other
problems but what's the diagnosis well
the diagnosis may be oh too much
turnover and maybe turnover is not so
bad if your developers have similar
training and if you have a shared set of
standards that you follow that you can
you know adhere to you know and that
they can adhere to but then in this case
as you're describing you know okay we
have technical debt why well the why is
the diagnosis and the diagnosis in this
case you were describing would be
there's so much turnover
but knowing that now this is that root
cause analysis it would be useful okay
why we have technical debt you know
using the financial analogy used in the
book is to me seems like a family that
keeps going deeper and deeper and deeper
into debt so just figuring out how to
satisfy the debt is at that point not
necessarily the only approach you want
to take you also want to say why do we
keep incurring debt what behaviors are
causing us to incur debt exactly and
that's also very important as i said
like the way you manage
why
is completely different the way okay how
do i really tackle this
problem that is happening in the code
base now right you still have to manage
what's like why do i keep getting into
that that's a different thing rather
than okay i have the debt myself now i
have to pay that down as well as
eliminate my ability to get more into
that
i guess situation after iteration or one
developer at a time or sure whichever
way it manifests itself in your
organization
now
perhaps this is pushing the analogy too
far but you tell me
not all debt is bad i mean if you make
an investment in something you know not
even just a mortgage but let's say you
buy a piece of investment property and
you take on debt in order to do so but
on that investment property you have a
building and you have a tenant and
you're getting more rent from the tenant
than you're paying on the debt for the
property
so in that case the debt is in a sense
good because it's allowing you to have
this investment does that apply at all
when we're talking about technical debt
of course and actually that's the power
of it not all that is bad and of course
i do not want to be
empowering everybody's technical debt
because like if i can stay in the se
radio show said no not all that is bad
but i think it's the really the
management aspects of it because it's
really software development is about
trade-offs and that's where i actually
are really related to the architecture
and design these are all about
trade-offs and we make trade-offs based
on all sorts of different priorities and
business concerns as well as other
technical concerns so technical that is
about having the vocabulary of
understanding those trade-offs and what
might be the consequences when those
trade-offs might change
if we don't manage it so if we're
comfortable with the notion that
software development and architecting is
about trade-offs
then if i'm making a trade-off that
might mean i might be taking on that
because i'm optimizing one over the
other the other attribute might still
turn out to be important but now i have
a vocabulary to say you know what i made
this trade off i need to
watch it carefully because the
priorities might change and should the
priorities change i need to revisit the
kinds of decisions i made so i think
from that perspective definitely
technical that is not all debt is bad
unintentional debt that is mostly bad
unmanaged debt is bad but being able to
understand the trade-offs and how you
express them
and create value out of them is actually
the power of the i think the metaphor as
well as any design activity and
technical that puts the concept around
it now if you're making this tradeoff
you have a vocabulary to express it did
we have not other vocabulary of course
we did we could still have put it in the
issue tracker and say okay here's an
architectural decision i made
but somehow i guess the negative
consequence didn't hit people
they always happen in some teams but i
never have seen it in about 20 years of
my software architecture research and
process and development as well as
organization work i haven't seen that as
a common practice i think technical that
concept gives us an opportunity to maybe
bring that to life
well and you mentioned putting an
architectural decision in an issue
tracker and i would encourage listeners
to read about architectural decision
records which i'm sure you're familiar
with and we can put a link to that in
the show notes
because in my experience yes in my
experience if it ends up in the issue
tracker it's going to go there to die
and no one's ever going to see it again
when they need it whereas if you put
your architectural decision records
right in your source code then they tend
to stick around a little longer and and
have a chance to be useful it doesn't
guarantee they will be but anyway so
that's correct and actually the same
goes for technical debt as well there's
work that has been done in terms of
looking into how developers actually
disclose their technical that in a part
of their comments what is the vocabulary
they use there's all sorts of typical
fix me this is a hack to do
and a significant portion of those are
actually also hints for technical debt
yeah absolutely yeah when you say slash
slash hack something yeah i'd reject
that pr out of hand but that's a whole
other side
so the next principle says if you do not
incur any form of interest then you
probably do not have actual technical
debt and that seems to make sense if
we're talking about debt then if you
have a debt you owe someone and you know
you aren't from a country or or a belief
system that doesn't allow interest then
you're going to be incurring interest if
you have a debt so the book uses this
analogy to try to help us i want to say
quantify but i don't know how explicitly
we can quantify technical debt but maybe
you can go a little bit further for us
in describing that analogy of principle
and interest and how that pertains to
managing technical debt so the interest
is about the consequences and the
principle if you do not incur any form
of interest you probably do not have
actual debts the key word is there the
actual and you just ask me about
technical debt not all being bad it
could actually be a potential value
creating activity that's actually
related to that so if i made a trade-off
and i recorded as a potential technical
debt at the moment i am not observing
the consequences
and by consequence again maybe i am
going through the actual development
life cycle maybe i just want to ship the
code so that i can actually observe how
the users are reacting to it at that
phase of the i guess system
there is no debt it's run when you start
seeing the consequences so it's really
that principle tries to
position the positive aspects of
technical debt and also actually provide
an opportunity it's not actual debt now
it's potential that in the future i
might need to revisit it so that's
really the differentiation and also when
you're reducing it that may not be the
top priority that you start from in your
rework because at the moment you're not
observing the consequences
okay
so is it actually possible to have a
system that's not incurring any interest
i don't think so because otherwise that
i think that would contradict the next
principle we're going to talk about
which is that all systems have technical
debt so you are you're always incurring
some interest you're always incurring
some interest on the technical debt
items it's just one particular design
decision i will refer to it as a design
decision you might say okay you know
what i'm taking this on
we will need to revisit it by the next
iteration
right at that moment that is actually
not incurring interest so it's potential
debt
and in the next situation you might say
you know what this is just fine so you
don't manage to does technical debt
anymore whether other items might be
observing consequences
it's really helpful too i think you know
you mentioned the term has been around
for a long time i myself have not really
thought about it in depth in relation to
finance but the more i think about it
now it seems like
if you're especially say in a startup
which i spent a lot of my career you
know doing startups
so
the idea is you're going to incur debt
or you're not going to be able to get
like anything done you know you're going
to have to make some trade-offs that's
just that's life there's always
trade-offs but you can also get into
technical debt bankruptcy and that's
called you failed
yeah right too much technical debt and
eventually it's just going to literally
blow up well there's that but jeff for
startup worlds i don't have as much
experience there it could be you might
have a beautiful system it's just a
business
need may not be there so well that's
right product market fit and those kinds
of things there's all sorts of things
the only reason you fail right there are
failures like i mean we went through
this the whole globally working from
home
and a lot of these systems that
supported us had to scale to
probably
limits that they didn't even imagine and
some of them were able to others weren't
able to so i think we've observed that
like business changes am i do i have a
product that did not incur technical
dead end could actually meet these new
needs at ease or i'm sure some of these
organizations had to go through very
painful conversations internally in
i guess pivoting or reworking or
solving the problems in different ways
well and it's tough too because if your
debt load is high you know i before i
use that analogy of a property owner
with a building and they rent it out to
someone but if they lose their tenant
and they can't find another one
before they didn't have too much debt
suddenly something happened and they
have way too much so i imagine that as
you're thinking about managing technical
debt here you could have it at a place
that seems healthy for the meantime but
something around you could change and
suddenly your debt load is too high so
that probably is i would imagine part of
managing technical debt too is wanting
to keep it at a reasonable again i know
we can't explicitly quantify it but some
sense of we are in control we are
managing this and if things change
around us we have a sense that we won't
be overly leveraged
and the way we refer to is there's an
expected baseline and ideal state that
the software development goes through
right it might be based on new
functionality that you deliver it might
be based on
the amount of i don't know code that
you're able to ship in different
organizations have different ways or
it's based on the new products that are
actually with the dateline whatever that
ideal state of delivery is that kind of
defines your problem with risk exposure
and then technical that is like does the
technical debt that you're accumulating
actually change that
ideal baseline that you have in terms of
how you are able to respond to the
needs of the organization with your
software development tempo
and then how does it actually change
that so i think that helps from a risk
exposure perspective different
organizations have different exposures
different organizations might be willing
to take more dead on sometimes they have
just complete sprints or iterations
dedicated to reworking the system to
reduce that there are different
strategies but it's really based on how
you're
able to take the risk and manage it and
the reason why technical that actually
is resonated with the developers
within the last decade more so than when
it was first voiced by cunningham in
1992 because it allowed them to talk
about it explicitly because everybody
knows that their software might have
issues but having the vocabulary to talk
explicitly help provided the opportunity
to manage it as well
so the next principle i think we've
addressed in some ways principle three
all systems have technical debt so maybe
the obvious question is why did you need
to explicitly call this out
because we've observed
mismanaged software systems over and
over again where the goal is to
really focus is the number rather than
the outcome of the software meeting its
business and mission and quality goals
so you're not really trying to first of
all we don't know how to actually even
assess zero defects through zero
technical that even uh with the tools
that we have at our exposure second the
systems we develop are complex
and they evolve in ways we do or do not
anticipate and that also is part of the
overall either management construct but
most importantly
as i said it's about trade-offs and
there's always a trade-off that happens
in every single system so every single
system has some amount of technical that
it could be well managed very low to
zero interest that's the ideal
or it could be not well managed where
you're actually really
struggling with some very difficult
quality issues as well as development
issues and that's really what the
differentiated we use the same similar
principle when we talk about software
architecture and systems every software
system has an architecture the
difference is whether you're aware of it
and whether you've designed it versus it
happens to you this is the same with
technical debt as well and you mentioned
systems multiple times and that's
perfect because the next principle says
technical debt must trace to the system
so maybe describe for us the importance
of that principle and what you mean by
by tracing it to the system
so this goes back to the earlier
conversation we already had the
confusion between what causes technical
debt and what's actually the rework that
i need to do to be able to reduce it and
also getting confused in terms of the
kitchen sink syndrome everything that
goes bad in my system is technical that
what we mean by there is like if we're
talking about a technical dead item i
should be able to concretely point in
the system what rework that i will need
to do if i don't manage that technical
debt okay so rather than just saying
there's that monolith over there that's
a pile of technical debt correct that's
pointing at the system but when you say
tracing to the system you mean more
specifically these are the portions of
the system that will need to be changed
in order to
address
the monolith yep i think the example you
give is a really good one
turn my monofilament to microservices
great
where do i start first of all is it even
helpful to manage this as a technical
that you're actually talking about a
serious re-architecting effort
which probably there's aspects of
technical debt within it but there's a
serious re-architecting going on so
that's number one there and what are the
specific things that need to be done and
i'm sure within the monolith there are
partials of it that are hairier to
resolve than others so differentiating
those actually would be some would be
technical that others would be just
routine development and re-architecting
effort sure and of course it'd be good
probably now to dispel the rumor as well
that microservices have less technical
depth than monoliths because regardless
of one or the other they both can have
their own
amounts of complexity and technical debt
so of course didn't want to imply one or
the other was better from a technical
debt please yes just using it as an
example yeah because with microservices
you could just say there they all are
there's the technical and that would be
just as bad as just pointing to the
monolith and dependency explosion
happens everywhere i think that's
probably
and honestly you talk about trade-offs
and that you focus on architecture and
so much of architecture i would distill
down to encapsulation and dependency
management and if you get those things
right you're gonna probably do better
than most exactly but i think i'm very
glad you picked up on that uh jeff
because there is no such thing as a
system developed with a microservice
architecture versus a monolith versus
service oriented architecture versus
whatever your most favorite
architectural paradigm is has more or
less technical that is a very irrelevant
question that's not the right question
to ask i'm following agile software
development versus my historic waterfall
whatever your most favorite software
development approach i have less or more
technical debt irrelevant question so
all of these and that's why it's
important every single system has
technical that it's that development
ecosystem and the activities
as well as the design trade-offs that
introduce it to the system well and back
to the first principle and why i think
this book is is helpful in in other ways
is it is making these abstract things
concrete but i think it's not always
abstract things being made concrete it's
confusing things being made clarified
and that's i think the issue with
monolith versus microsystems or agile
versus waterfall is often those words
they're a lot of times straw men they
don't they don't even relate to the
thing as it really was and i think
that's true about both agile and
waterfall in many cases so in a similar
fashion we're saying let's talk let's
actually define what techno that is and
then we can actually deal with it once
we actually know what it is and what it
isn't that's actually exactly why some
of these principles
reinforce
get specific get concrete trace it to
the system don't stay at the abstract
level because then you'll have the tools
to
deal with
whatever the consequences or whatever
the technical debt that you're incurring
and more importantly you'll also have
the tools to manage with some of the
other issues that you might actually not
have the vocabulary to manage before so
that's really the point of the
principles as well as the book
sponsor for this episode is spot by
netapp spot provides a comprehensive
suite of cloud ops tools that make it
easy to deliver continuously optimized
and reliable infrastructure at the
lowest possible cost imagine automating
your infrastructure to proactively meet
the needs of your applications imagine
leveraging the latest in machine
learning and automation to scale your
infrastructure using the most efficient
mix of instances and pricing models
eliminating the risks of
over-provisioning and expensive lock-in
from cost management to infrastructure
automation and cd to running serverless
spark on kubernetes spot ensures you
maximize your cloud investment the end
result is simply more cloud at less cost
discover how the most innovative
companies from cloud native growth
machines to forward thinking enterprises
are automating simplifying and
optimizing their cloud infrastructures
with spot by netapp
check them out at spot.io se radio where
you can find more information request a
demo or give a try by starting a free
trial
and that leads right into principle five
technical debt is not synonymous with
bad quality so we talked before you
can't just point at the system say
there's all the debt you have to trace
it to these are the parts of the system
that are impacted by or need to be you
know changed in order to satisfy this
technical that these kinds of things
but now you're also saying it's not
synonymous with bad quality so why why
is that why wouldn't we just say bad
quality is technical debt why aren't
those the same thing so this goes back
to reinforcing if you're talking about
technical debt more often than not
you're talking about the structure and
the behavior the architecture of the
system so bad quality is bad bad quality
obviously there but we also have tools
to deal with bad quality right we have
quality assurance practices defect
management quality conformance all those
static code checkers or whatever is your
most favorite approach to manage that
those often tend to be symptoms why
there are symptoms because you have bad
quality you probably have also not
structured your software properly it
really
hints at an underlying structure and
behavior problem in the way the software
is organized as well so that's number
one number two
early on when we started working and
trying to
understand the concepts around it there
was a tendency okay fine i'm going to go
to my defects all my defects are now
called technical debt technical debt is
not all bad i'm done so there's that
tendency to kind of confuse concepts
with each other as well so we wanted to
decouple it the other tendency was there
are quite a number of quite powerful
static code analyzers that will actually
hint at some of these issues some of
them again might be symptoms but again
all right i run my most favorite tool on
my code code base it came up with 11 000
number of conformance issues
and it says the cost of the fixing them
is twice the cost of the development
effort
i'm already bankrupt so those
wrong ways of measuring and mapping them
actually does not help anybody so the
reason of that principle is trying to
decouple it of course it's one thing to
make these very easy examples there are
some cases where things get hairy but i
think experienced developers and
software engineers have already
the appreciation to be able to decouple
them and deal with them
in terms of whether technical debt or
whatever else issue that they might
actually have at hand
and with that it reminds me of the
distinction between data information and
knowledge you know static analysis tool
might give you data it might give you
information but it doesn't give you
knowledge
and it seems to me that technical debt
is and the way you're describing it and
the way the book is you know teaching us
to think about it and manage it it's
helping us move from that data to
information to actual knowledge
which is good because now it's
actionable and we can identify it and we
can have conversations where we actually
mean the same things by the words that
we're using which is helpful if you want
to actually communicate
and you can even god forbid i use the
word
quantify it because now i know what i
need to change and i can actually get
concrete not be overwhelmed by the
thousands of issues that i put on my in
front of me and my software has bad
quality which i might already know
actually that my software has bad
quality
right and the quantification of course
and i know you you you know shudder
maybe to say it but this is more of a
generalized quantification you know this
isn't precision down to you know
nanometers or something like that but
it's a general
sense of you know we can we can sort of
size it we have a sense of the size
right i can prioritize it i can decide
whether i'm going to do it this sprint
or that
sprint and i know which developer
will be able to handle it with how many
number of days and whatever so that's
the level of quantification i mean yeah
so i know principle six is uh near and
dear to both of our hearts as software
architects
so the principle says architecture
technical debt has the highest cost of
ownership can you tell us a little bit
more about what you mean with that
principle definitely first of all for
the listeners i should probably clarify
when i refer to technical that i am
actually referring to the architectural
and design constructs however what has
happened in the community is
when people identify technical debt
depending on the artifact like for
example i do a code analysis and that's
how i'm talking about technical that i
call it my code debt if i'm talking
about my infrastructure i call it my
deployment debt or my security debt
i think that actually creates and adds
to the confusion
there are two reasons one we're talking
when we're talking about technical that
we're talking about rework and the
trade-offs that it enforces and also
when we talked about okay quality
relates to some of the structure and
behavior of the software
or when we say when you have all sorts
of complexity added to the software you
incur technical debt we're always
talking about these accumulated design
aspects of it so that's important and
also why it's highest because it becomes
layers and layers of implementation on
top of a wrong structure to start with
reworking that actually has a lot of
accumulation so for both reasons
architecture has the highest cost of all
ownership technical that is about
architecture more than other things you
might be discovering technical debt
through other artifacts but at the end
resolution is often architectural so
that principle is trying to
highlight that strong relationship
between technical and architectural
design choices
so if we had cost on the vertical axis
and we had poor design on the left of
the x and
good design going towards the right of
the x-axis then we would basically see
that the highest point on the curve
would be poor design
and it would slope down as you got
closer to improved and better design
correct okay so if you want a high cost
of ownership on your system design it
poorly
and we are not the first to actually
point that out there all sorts of even
the flow and lean software methodologies
have actually put today it's really the
backlog and how you're pulling things
and what is the rate of addressing some
of these issues that also are related to
how you're bringing the cast on with
good design
principle seven all code matters really
i mean my code matters more than others
i can hear people thinking no but any
but seriously like what kind of code is
there that isn't treated like it doesn't
matter this again i mean all principles
we went through multiple situations
there's actually i've been conversations
that felipe brought and i had through
them all all code matters because
resolving technical that or discovering
is not just on the code or not the first
of all it's really you need to bring it
back to the implementation yet
for example the test code matters there
as well because we've actually have
examples where developers tweak the test
code to make the test pass but it
actually was on hiding technical debt so
there's that traceability between the
implementation the test and the
infrastructure there's a lot of now with
the cicd and the devops age we're going
through a lot of build and
infrastructure codes that actually can
incur technical debts which might uh
hinder your ability to develop and the
tempo that you're actually developing at
so it's really a technical that maps to
the rework that you need to do in the
code and it's thought through in the
from the design concept so that's really
what we're trying to emphasize but
mostly it was our observation that
we allow
lower bar on test and infrastructure
code which i think in the long run
creates more negative outcomes rather
than positive ones
and to your previous points
that involves architecture meaning you
have an architecture for your
infrastructure code and you have an
architecture for your test code it just
may not be a good one
correct and that will show in pain and
when you see that pain you can start to
say ah there's some debt here there's
some technical that here because the
design is showing us
pain
and the alignment also right when i fix
my code did i actually align my tests
and build infrastructure with the fixes
i made and sometimes there's all sorts
of mismatches that happen with that
alignment that we've observed actually
created significant issues and sometimes
the time spent is not necessarily on the
fixing that but the time spent is
finding where the issues are because of
the misalignment that might be
introduced in the process right and i
think this principle helps too because
you know we've talked a lot about
systems and i think that's part of the
point here is a system is going to have
a lot of code of different kinds and
qualities and sometimes some people
might have a tendency to say well my
code matters
or the code i understand matters or the
code in front of me matters but we're
building a system
and so even though i might be developing
you know a specific piece of
functionality for the system in code
that doesn't mean i can ignore
deployment pipelines because there might
be an impact say you know some helm
chart out there i mean maybe i don't
know everything about how kubernetes
runs
but i also can't say it doesn't matter
because it's someone else's
role or task or whatever right that code
still matters
correct and actually it also relates
itself to when you actually have to
interface with external systems a
typical example we use to demonstrate
this is in a
example system that we worked with
the system crashes developers identify
it patch it the system crashes again for
the same reason
developers identify patchett after quite
a number of patches i think the number
was 28 or something one of the
developers say you know what something
else is going on here well the crash was
injected to the system because of an api
with an external software system they
never patched it in the source hence
they kept actually having have to find
what was going on so this is again the
fix is not difficult finding the root
cause of the fix within the system is
difficult and all code matters because
it's not even called your own it's
called to you actually come from an
external system well and i think too it
relates to quality in a in an
interesting way you know i think of the
the o-ring problem with the space
shuttle and my understanding although i
might have to to verify this is that the
o-rings used on the space shuttle were
also used all the way back in the apollo
program and the only reason they didn't
discover it back then is because they
didn't have the rocket go through a
period of freezing temperatures and it
was only when that occurred that we
finally had the columbia disaster or was
it the challenger disaster it was a
challenger disaster in the 80s so in a
similar way in that case all components
matter i mean a simple o-ring a simple
quote-unquote o-ring in a complex system
led to catastrophe
and i think in a similar way here if we
say all code doesn't matter we might
just be setting ourselves up for
catastrophe in ways we cannot yet
envision or imagine
and also we see this a lot with legacy
software because
way back when
for example to optimize for performance
not all of the security
principles were implemented the way they
were like they were disabled for one
reason or another because we didn't have
as powerful processes and whatnot but
now we have still the same software
but we have more opportunities for
attackers and those areas because
actually
issues in the software system again
at the time if we had the vocabulary
those implementers could have said you
know what we're disabling these things
to optimize performance should our
hardware and software change please
enable them again so that we don't have
to deal with some of the consequences i
think those subtleties become important
as software evolves as well
and that's a wonderful point because
that expands the meaning of this to
another level it's it's meta all code
matters meaning all the code everywhere
ever written
matters
because you never know which of that
code could create
a problem for you even if you're not
involved in the development of the
system when you think of disasters that
are software related literally you're
saying
all code matters and it goes back to the
earlier conversation we had with the
software crisis why do we have software
crisis because we go through these
evolutions at the time we're doing the
right thing like in this example
disabling the checks was the right thing
because we're trying to optimize for
performance latency which is important
for the software's behavior yet now we
have a different situation if we have
the vocabulary to express it the new
owners of the software will actually
know what to check for what to look for
and know where they are located because
now there's a vocabulary to be able to
actually trace it so that's it's really
about all code matters and the
collective ownership not within the team
but i guess within the overall life
cycle of the software system
well let's move on to principle eight
which says technical debt has no
absolute measure
neither for principle nor interest and
of course this is why previously when we
mentioned quantification i know we both
kind of backed away from that a little
bit but if it has no absolute measure
we've spoken a little bit about
principle and interest but talk to us a
little bit more now about how we can
measure it even if we don't have
absolute measures for it
so one of the things that early on a lot
of the organizations got excited about
is like okay great now i have the
vocabulary technical that i'm going to
run a tool press a button it's going to
tell me the dollar amount i am going to
compare this with the other software i'm
going to decide or i'm going to compare
this with whatever i'm being delivered i
will pay or pay not so
i am very sorry to disappoint everyone
who's looking for this that is never
going to happen
what measurement comes down to is first
of all recording it if we start
recording it explicitly then we'll know
how much of our systems development
effort is going into technical debt but
the other is being able to understand
what rework means right when am i going
to rework the each technical dead item
and what does it mean and how
cumulatively and as the number of items
that appear mean in terms of the
measurement the principle which is at
the time when you're taking technical
debt that's actually even harder
because systems will evolve and
resolving the debt might actually be a
different architecture lower design
strategy than what you have already once
started with so that's not an apple
strapless comparison let me bring back
the financial metaphor if i'm taking ten
thousand dollars of uh debt i'm paying
back 10 000 plus its interest in the
software sense if i'm making a design
trade-off picking one over the other
when i do a different design choice i
may not actually be redoing in the same
way i might alcohol have a completely
different approach to it so that's
really trying to put them as apples to
apples comparison is difficult i think
finally we're moving away from it i see
more and more development teams
recognizing okay let's at least
enumerate what we mean what we are
talking about when we're talking about
technical debt so we can measure the
consequences we can measure the rework
we can definitely measure some of the
downstream impacts of technical debt but
comparing them between different systems
or trying to think that this particular
system has an amount of technical that
is not the right way to think about it
and the book we can't obviously go into
all the details that's why listeners
will need to get a copy of the book but
there are helpful diagrams and also
helpful conversations about different
sizes of companies or different sizes of
systems and the kinds of technical that
they they might incur and my question
there is i think i recall but but tell
me if i'm misremembering here that
there's even possibly different
measurements for the different sizes of
companies or different things you're
going to focus on is that correct of
course i mean it's really the
fundamentally how you're looking into
the consequences and your
ideal development
i guess baseline that you're talking
about in one organization
the consequence of technical debt might
actually incur as you are not able to
add new functionality fast enough in
another organization the consequence of
technical that might incur as you keep
is observing more defects because
there's relationship with some of these
in another organization it might
actually be so complex that you are not
able to onboard developers so what it
actually the consequence maps to might
be different so there are different
metrics the good news is these metrics
or these measurement techniques are not
foreign to the software engineers we
already have these that are disposable
we are already doing it we're already
using some of the devops pipelines and
introducing tools to do some of these
checks it's really stepping back and as
you said what is the knowledge that
those information is providing us that
would actually be worthwhile to
communicate to the rest of the system
developers as well as other stakeholders
as okay here's a technical dead item and
we need to talk about this
at our sprint as well as as we're doing
our planning for
our resource allocation
and the final principle is technical
debt depends on the future evolution of
the system how can we depend on the
future when we don't know the future
that's a good question and i think it's
about the accumulation of the
consequences and the rework so
when we decide whether i would like to
actually
reduce
or rework this particular aspect of the
system or not we're making a decision
even today without the technical that
concept we're making the decision based
on our anticipated use of the system
in the future so that anticipated use
puts a stress or not on the particular
system with or without technical debt
and i assess it based on that
anticipated use and rework because if i
don't anticipate that part of the system
that has technical debt to change often
or the consequences not observed then i
would not have any reason to spend
resources on paying it down
so that's really what it's trying to
emphasize and that's how we make our
decisions when we're making our other
system
prioritization decisions as well so it's
not just unique to technical that it's
actually the way our planning works
well we've also talked a lot about
design and architecture so i imagine in
good design
so you know future evolution
wouldn't that be constrained somewhat by
a better design which would then affect
the impact of technical debt on you
going forward meaning the evolution of
the system will be constrained somewhat
by the architecture and the design of
the system of course yes yes and that's
actually the moment you put a design or
version one system out there you're
already providing constraints
to how you're actually going to evolve
it and then the question is well whether
you'll be able to live with those
constraints that the current
architecture poses versus whether you
need to relax these concerns which is
re-architect and rework the system
yeah and i'd point listeners back to a
previous episode with yuval loewy on his
book writing software where he talks
about ways that you can define these
components of your system or these these
interfaces and contracts between the
systems in ways that actually can help
you constrain the system so that as it
evolves you're not constantly evolving
your architecture because if you're
constantly involved in your architecture
your your system is going to be unwieldy
and complex and and you're probably
going to have a lot of technical debt
and that's also you mentioned earlier a
good design actually reduces your risk
of taking on technical debt because
you've made some of these trade-offs
early on this doesn't mean design
upfront this doesn't mean you don't
evolve your system but it really is
really understanding what are some of
the constraints understanding dry
architectural drivers understanding how
they will actually which ones might
change which may not change sure well
and you mentioned design upfront i'd
clarify that with big design upfront
which is also i think become a straw man
and a boogeyman and it gets bandied
about just like yagni you ain't gonna
need it and what ends up happening is no
design up front and i think what we need
is just enough or you know some design
up front that's enough but definitely
not no design as a response to too much
design
listeners may or may not agree with me
on this these are my personal i guess
beliefs that i'm very strongly become i
guess standing behind them when you're
talking about technical debt you're
really talking about and design and
architecture trade-offs and their rework
consequences own it that's number one
and number two is
assuming that you don't know anything
and things will emerge
is really not looking into your problem
uh carefully enough there are always
things that will not change as quickly
as you anticipate and there will always
be some of the drivers that will
actually be there that will help you
make the design choices early on and
then you can iterate on it and
continuously evolve the system but
assuming that you will not you know
nothing about to be able to make
architectural decisions
is probably a naive perspective
so if i'm a listener and i want to begin
taking action based on what i've learned
and i want to get a copy of the book and
and have some next steps my first
question might be
this sounds like a lot of work
identifying technical debt and tracking
technical debt and quantifying technical
even though it's not absolute but some
quantification so what's your response
to listeners for say different sides of
system or different sizes of team
you know who obviously would have
different constraints in that regard but
if they say this just seems too daunting
i'm not going to take the time how do
you respond to them so i would
appreciate if it's dawning from the
perspective of okay i have never heard
of the concept so how do i relate it
with things i know that i have some
appreciation for because in a way
technical debt puts the concepts that
we've already known i said architectural
trade-offs design trade-offs software
maintainability and rework
with a different eye so that there's
vocabulary so that i might appreciate
until they've done some homework however
the rest i think we already do anyways
developers already talk about technical
that developers already talk about
aspects of their system that is hard to
rework they already know
i think all these little concepts that
are introduced into the comments hacked
me to do this is
bad
with all sorts of vocabulary so there's
actually already existing
techniques existing practices that we
have just i think if they want to do one
thing
that one thing is start
putting technical debt to whatever
system that you're using to communicate
tasks
user stories defects whatever you call
them
into whatever system you're using
and identify it with a clear label
that's why you at least have okay
are we overdoing it are we on the same
page are we really identifying things
that are going to
cause us pain in the long run that will
create information for the team and
that's really not a very daunting task
and after that you can use whatever
you're using already as part of your
software project management
and software release planning iteration
planning practices it's really that easy
from that perspective
right so as i was saying before we were
discussing design you want just enough
design i imagine it's similar here with
management if you're a small team versus
a large team your technical debt
management principles might differ
and also
if you're a small team you it might be
good enough just to talk to each other
versus if you're a large team and
running a large organization there's
more coordination and organization
needed and obviously then the
consequences also
snowball a lot quicker as well
right but the book would still be
helpful for the small team i imagine
from the standpoint of
clarifying what they're talking about
even if talking about is all they need
to do
and also to make sure that
i would assume a small team might be a
startup right and if you really want to
be a large team
what do you really need to be able to be
aware of in that role so i think small
teams might take all different flavors
as well depending on what kind of a
domain you're in but yes i think
regardless of the team size and the
project size i think this is a
fundamental
concept that we need to teach our
software engineers
and that's also important to recognize
well if people want to find out more
about what you're up to where can they
go
i work at carnegie mellon university
software engineering institute all of
the practices that we develop are
actually available we share that's why
it's exciting to be in this show so that
we can actually share some of this
knowledge with our listeners as well and
our website is www.sci
and our blog post podcasts as well as
some of the papers that we've written
including case studies are available
there
as well as the book if anybody is
interested great
well thanks so much for joining me today
on software engineering radio epec
well thanks for having me jeff
this is jeff doolittle for software
engineering radio thanks for listening
thanks for listening to sc radio an
educational program brought to you by
ieee software magazine
for more about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website at se
radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on linkedin facebook twitter or through
our slack channel at scradio.slack.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of sc radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening